We've now got our document
split up into small, semantically
meaningful chunks, and
it's time to put these chunks
into an index, whereby we
can easily retrieve them when it
comes time to answer questions about
this corpus of data. To do
that, we're going to utilize embeddings and vector
stores. Let's see what those
are. We covered this briefly
in the previous course,
but we're going to revisit it
for a few reasons. First, these are incredibly
important for building chatbots over
your data. And
second, we're going to go a
bit deeper, and we're going to talk about
edge cases,
and where this generic method can actually
fail. Don't worry, we're
going to fix those later
on.
But for now, let's talk about vector
stores and embeddings. And
this comes after text splitting, when
we're ready to store the
documents in an easily accessible format.
What embeddings
are? They take
a piece of text, and they
create a numerical representation
of that text. Text
with similar content will have
similar vectors in this
numeric space. What that
means is we can
then compare those vectors
and find pieces of
text that are similar. So, in the
example below, we can
see that the two
sentences about pets are
very similar, while a
sentence about a pet and
a sentence about a car
are not very similar. As a
reminder of the full end-to-end workflow, we start
with documents,
we then create smaller
splits of those documents,
we then create embeddings
of those documents, and then we
store all of those in a
vector store. A vector store is
a database where you
can easily look up
similar vectors later on.
This will become useful
when we're trying to find documents
that are relevant for
a question at hand.
We can then take the
question at hand, create an embedding, and then
do comparisons to
all the different vectors
in the vector store,
and then pick the n
most similar. We then take those n
most similar chunks, and
pass them along with
the question into an LLM,
and get back an answer.
We'll cover all of that later
on. For now, it's time to deep
dive on embeddings and vector stores themselves.
To start, we'll once again set the
appropriate environment variables. From
here on out, we're going
to be working with the
same set of documents. These are
the CS229 lectures. We're going to
load a few of them here. Notice that we're
actually going to
duplicate the first lecture.
This is for the
purposes of simulating some dirty
data. After the documents are
loaded, we can then use
the recursive character text
splitter to create chunks.
We can see that
we've now created over 200 different chunks. Time
to move on to
the next section and create
embeddings for all of them.
We'll use OpenAI to create these
embeddings. Before jumping into a real-world
example,
let's try it out with
a few toy
test cases just to get
a sense for what's going
on underneath the hood. We've got a
few example sentences where the first two
are very similar and
the third one is
unrelated.
We can then use
the embedding class to
create an embedding for
each sentence.
We can then use NumPy to compare them,
and see which ones are most similar.
We expect that the first two
sentences should be very similar,
and then the first and second
compared to the third shouldn't
be nearly as similar. We'll use
a dot product to compare
the two embeddings. If you
don't know what
a dot product is, that's fine. The important
thing to know is that higher is
better. Here we can see
that the first two embeddings
have a pretty high score
of 0.96. If we compare the first
embedding to the third one,
we can see that it's
significantly lower at 0.77. And
if we compare the second to
the third, we can see it's right about
the same at 0.76. Now
is a good time to pause, and try
out a few sentences of your own,
and see what the dot product is. Let's
now get back to the real-world example. It's
time to create embeddings for all the chunks
of the PDFs
and then store them in
a vector store.
The vector store that we'll
use for this lesson is Chroma. So,
let's import that. LangChain has
integrations with lots, over 30
different vector stores. We choose
Chroma because it's lightweight and
in memory, which makes it
very easy to get up
and started with. There are other
vector stores that offer
hosted solutions, which can be
useful when you're trying to persist
large amounts of data or persist
it in cloud storage somewhere. We're
going to want to
save this vector store
so that we can
use it in future lessons. So, let's create
a variable called persist directory, which we
will use later on
at docs slash Chroma. Let's
also just make sure that nothing
is there already. If there's
stuff there already, it can
throw things off and we don't
want that to happen. So, let's RM dash
RF docs dot Chroma just to make
sure that there's nothing there. Let's
now create the vector store. So, we
call Chroma from documents,
passing in splits, and these are the
splits that we created earlier,
passing in embedding.
And this is the
open AI embedding model
and then passing in
persist directory, which is a Chroma
specific keyword argument that
allows us to save
the directory to disk.
If we take a look at
the collection count after doing this,
we can see that it's 209, which
is the same as the number of splits
that we had from before. Let's now
start using it. Let's think of
a question that we can ask
of this data. We know that
this is about a class lecture. So, let's
ask if there is any email that
we can ask for help if we need
any help with the course or material or
anything like that. We're
going to use the
similarity search method, and
we're going to pass
in the
question, and then we'll also pass in
K equals three.
This specifies the number of documents that
we want to
return. So, if we run that
and we look at the length of the documents,
we can see that it's three as
we specified. If we take
a look at the content
of the first document, we can
see that it is in fact
about an email address, cs229-qa.cs.stanford.edu. And
this is the email that we
can send questions to and
is read by all the TAs.
After doing so, let's make sure to persist
the vector database so
that we can use it in future lessons
by running vectordb.persist. This has
covered the basics of semantic search
and shown us that we can
get pretty good results based on
just embeddings alone. But it
isn't perfect and here we'll go over a
few edge cases and show where
this can fail. Let's try a new
question. What did they say about
MATLAB? Let's run this specifying K equals
five and get back
some results. If we
take a look at
the first two results, we
can see that they're actually
identical. This is because when
we loaded in
the PDFs, if you
remember, we specified on purpose
a duplicate entry. This is bad
because we've got the
same information in two different
chunks and we're going to
be passing both of these chunks
to the language model down
the line.
There's no real value in
the second piece of
information and it would
be much better if there was a different
distinct chunk that the
language model could learn from. One
of the things that we'll cover
in the next lesson is how to retrieve
both relevant and distinct
chunks at the same
time. There's another type
of failure mode that can
also happen. Let's take a look
at the question, what did they say
about regression in the third
lecture? When we get the
docs for this, intuitively we would expect
them to all be
part of the third lecture. We can check
this because we have information
in the metadata about
what lectures they came
from. So, let's loop over all
the documents and print out the
metadata. We can see that
there's actually a combination of results,
some from the third lecture, some
from the second lecture, and
some from the first. The
intuition about why this is
failing is that the third lecture
and the fact that we want
documents from only the third lecture
is a piece
of structured information, but we're just
doing a semantic lookup based
on embeddings where it
creates an embedding for
the whole sentence and
it's probably a bit
more focused on regression.
Therefore, we're getting results
that are probably pretty
relevant to
regression and so if
we take a look
at the fifth doc, the one that comes
from the first lecture, we
can see that it
does in fact mention
regression. So, it's picking up
on that, but it's not picking
up on the fact that it's only supposed
to be querying documents from the third lecture because
again, that's a piece
of structured information that
isn't really perfectly captured in
this semantic embedding that we've
created. Now's a good
time to pause and try out
a few more queries.
What other edge
cases can you notice that arise?
You can also play
around with changing k,
the number of documents that you
retrieve. As you may have
noticed throughout this lesson,
we used first three and then five.
You can try adjusting it
to be whatever you want. You'll
probably notice that when
you make it larger, you'll retrieve
more documents, but the
documents towards the tail end
of that may not be
as relevant as the ones
at the beginning. Now, that we've
covered the basics of semantic search
and also some of
the failure modes, let's go on to
the next lesson. We'll talk about how to
address those failure modes
and beef up our
retrieval.